<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sorts of latter days, proved from Scripture. First, the latter days of perilous times, the which are to be ended before the great and glorious latter days have their beginning. Proved when the elder people or nation is to serve the younger. And by that servitude made blessed. The old and new testament made to agree. And truth vindicated against all heresies. By M. Marsin</title>
            <author>Marsin, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M813E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834027</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834027</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1836:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sorts of latter days, proved from Scripture. First, the latter days of perilous times, the which are to be ended before the great and glorious latter days have their beginning. Proved when the elder people or nation is to serve the younger. And by that servitude made blessed. The old and new testament made to agree. And truth vindicated against all heresies. By M. Marsin</title>
                  <author>Marsin, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by J. Bradford in Little-Britain, the Corner House over against the pump. Mrs. Michael at the Crown and Cushion in Westminster-Hall. And at Mercers-Chappel in Cheapside. At John Gwillum's over against the Great James in Bishopsgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi⁴ B-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heresies, Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38506:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two SORTS OF <hi>Latter Days,</hi> PROVED FROM SCRIPTURE: FIRST, THE Latter Days of Perilous Times, THE WHICH Are to be Ended before the Great and Glorious LATTER DAYS have their Beginning.</p>
            <p>Proved when the <hi>Elder People</hi> or <hi>Nation</hi> is to <hi>ſerve the Younger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND By That SERVITUDE made BLESSED. The Old and New Teſtament made to Agree. AND TRUTH Vindicated againſt all HERESIES.</p>
            <p>By <hi>M. MARSIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Bradford</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> the Corner Houſe, over againſt the Pump. Mrs. <hi>Michael</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Cuſhion</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> And at <hi>Mercers Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> At <hi>John Gwillum</hi>'s, over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Great James</hi> in <hi>Biſhopsgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38506:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38506:2"/>
            <head>The Dedication.</head>
            <p>IT is humbly offered his Majeſty, and the great Council of the Nation, that if there is any other place of Scripture which is not anſwered in this nor my other Book, if it ſtand in any oppoſition to the Scriptures agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to hinder the Witneſs of the Apoſtles from agreeing with the Teſtimony of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (which is the ſure word of Propheſie. <hi>2 Pet. 1.19.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which the Chriſtians were always to take heed, ſo as to believe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in contradiction thereunto) by God's aſſiſtance it will be made plain. And I hope that neither his Majeſty, nor the Nobles, nor the Clergy will be offended that God ſhould bring theſe great Truths to Light by ſo weak an Inſtrument; for God often makes uſe of ſuch to declare great things by, that ſo his Power thereby might be the more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſeen. For had God by the Wiſe and Learned Doctors of the time removed all the
<pb facs="tcp:38506:3"/>miſtaken Notions; and made his Word to agree, which Man had made ſo much to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree: And likewiſe explained the Viſion ſo plain from the word, it would have been thought it had proceeded from their great Parts and Learning: Therefore God chuſes the weak things of this World, that all the Praiſe may be rendered to his Name: And it being every ones concern to underſtand the great Truths of God'<hi>s</hi> word: Therefore it is deſired that into whoſe hands ſoever this Book ſhall come, that they will Read it: But eſpecially it is more humbly requeſted of all to whom it is preſented, that they will read it themſelves, becauſe it is of very great import; and I hope they will reap Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by it. God bleſs the King and Great Council, and remember the Jews in Mercy according to his Promiſes made to their Fathers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38506:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO know the Scriptures aright, is the great concern of Chriſtians, the which by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from the Truth, the right Sentiments of the Word have been loſt, which miſtaken places have ſince lain as dark Mountains, on which the Chriſtians have ſtumbled. And every one hath made an interpretation of them according to their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Whereby they have ſet the Scriptures at an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable difference, the which has occaſion'd ſome to turn <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Papists,</hi> ſome <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and ſome Prophane. So as thereby now there are but three ſorts of People that can believe: The firſt are thoſe that have always walked in a Holy Converſation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they have had experiences of God. The ſecond, are thoſe that fall under a Terror of Conſcience: The third are thoſe, who through the ignorance in the Scriptures, each believeth what their. Teachers tell them; whether they be <hi>Papists, Proteſtants,</hi> or any other Sect. But for any rational Man to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the ſtrange interpretation put upon them: by which they have made the Oaths, and Words, and Promiſes of God void, that Man muſt deny the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that God hath given him, if he can believe the Strange Tenets, that are held concerning them, and whilſt we deny ſo many plain Truths in God's Word, it is very improbable that the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſhould ever be convinced by what we ſay. For as by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Apoſtaſie, they have impoſed upon the People
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38506:4"/>their falſe Worſhip, and others having impoſed upon the People their miſtaken Notions, that they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with, the which is as a Bridle put into the Jaws of the People, cauſing them to err, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.28. For the <hi>Protestants</hi> are as much afraid to look into the Truth, and to conſider it for fear of being led into Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, as the Papiſts are to eat Fleſh in <hi>Lent.</hi> And this fear like a Bridle, keeps them in Error. But when God according to his promiſe at the time of the end, brings the Knowledge of the true meaning of his word to light, whereby the Scriptures are made to agree in a Holy Harmony; the Teachers that will not take the Bridle out of the Jaws of the People, muſt expect to fall under the ſame Puniſhment, as thoſe that put it in; And therefore that our Teachers may not be found guilty of the great Tranſgreſſion, the which is wilful diſobedience, to oppoſe or ſmother the Truth, when God in his own way, and at his own time brings again the great Truths in his Word to Light, that knowledge thereby might be increaſed, and Man prepared; I therefore will here ſet down ſome of thoſe Texts of Scripture that relate to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Ambaſſadors of Peace in our time; becauſe what is ſpoken is about, and at the time of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration: and therefore muſt have its chief reference to our Teachers in this Day, and it is our Miniſters that are reamed Shepherds and Ambaſſadors of Peace: For <hi>Iſraels</hi> Prieſts were never ſent of any ſuch Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. And therefore, that I may clear my ſelf from the Blood of all Men in what God hath employed me in, I ſhall here cite the Places that relate to them that will oppoſe, or ſmother the Truth. For theſe following Scriptures belong to the Chriſtians, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.9, 10, 11. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. the whole Chap. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.16, 17, 18. <hi>Fear, and the Pit and the Snare, are upon thee, O inhabitant of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38506:4"/>
            <p>I have with fervent and earneſt Prayer, wreſtled with the moſt High God that he would ſend Peace, that the great Truths of God might be conſidered, and if they are not, he will require it.</p>
            <p>And it is God's uſual way and method, <hi>to chuſe the weak things of this World to confound the Wiſe and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> For it was the Rulers, and Seers, when they came to have no Love to the Truth, that firſt laid the Chriſtian World in Darkneſs; <hi>So as the Viſion of ill becamed Sealed:</hi> Therefore God declared that the Rulers and Seers he hath covered, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10, 11. whereby is ſhewed, that the Viſion of all, is not to come forth that way. And therefore ſo many Good, Wiſe, and Learned Men, have come no nearer the mark of the Truth, in this matter. For as when Chriſt firſt came, <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Prieſts did not rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the manner of his coming; neither was it at firſt declared to, or by them; tho' without doubt there were ſeveral good ones amongſt them.</p>
            <p>And if Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, could have made the Scriptures agree, the Scholars of all parties would not have ſo much diſagreed about them: but ſince the Apoſtaſie from the Truth, the Wifeſt and Beſt of Men could not do it. But God can give the Simple, Wiſdom when he pleaſeth. And with him, there is neither Bond nor Free, Male nor Female, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. But the ſincere Heart, that truly loves and fears him, is beſt accepted of him. And God hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing employed me in his Service, I am willing to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture all, even Life and all for him, that the Truth of God's Word may be known. And to be ſure it is rightly underſtood, when the Scriptures are made to agree, and thereby they become plain to a rational Man's underſtanding: which is the Light that God hath ſet up in the Soul of Man. That thereby he might know how to chuſe the Good, and refuſe the Evil. And the Scriptures now being made to agree,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38506:5"/>and God by his Word according to his Promiſe proved true, as well to the <hi>Jews,</hi> as to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> This may be convincing to any rational Man's underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that believes the Scriptures, it they will but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the matter.</p>
            <p>Some ſay let the Prophet take care of his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But ſuch little think that their deſtruction is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in it, if they do not take heed of the Prophet's warning. But there is no way to bring the People to a right underſtanding of the Truth, but by unravel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to them their miſtakes to the bottom. For our Authors having loſt the right Apprehenſion of the World, or Time to come; then they were put to their ſhifts, like the Wits of the Times, to weather out a Cauſe, when they had neither Truth nor Tackle to aſſiſt their invention. By which miſtakes, <hi>The Sheep of the Lord, eat that which others have trodden, and drink that which others have fouled with their feet, Ezek.</hi> 34.18, 19. So as thereby all are in miſtakes at this Day, for this is ſpoken concerning the time the Lord will Judge between the <hi>Rams</hi> and the <hi>He-Goats,</hi> after which time the Lord will for evermore feed his Sheep himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23, 24, 25.</p>
            <p>But now ſome by Studying the Scriptures, with the ſtrange interpretations which our great Authors (as ſome call them) have put upon them, have loſt their Senſes. And others fearing they are not elected; and if not, they then think they were reprobated from all Eternity, or from the Foundation of the World. The which have drove many into diſpair, and cauſed ſome to make themſelves away. But the knowledge of the Truth of God's word ſets all free from ſuch ill conſequences: And likewiſe puts them that know the Truth, into a good capacity for eternal Salvation: For to a true Faith, there is required ſound Doctrine, as well as good Practice, and to believe what God hath ſaid, and ſworn to, before what any Man ſaith in contradiction thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38506:5"/>
            <closer>
               <signed>The weight of this great affair, I hope will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which is the deſire, and earneſt Prayer of your Friend and Servant in Chriſt, <hi>M. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>All that are willing to know the Truth, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of them to conſider theſe Twelve things.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> THat we are not the <hi>Elect,</hi> but that the <hi>Elect</hi> was the Remnant choſen from among <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which is the Church in the Wilderneſs, and the firſt Gentile Churches, unto whom the Holy Ghoſt was given to be in them, that they might be a light to the World, that the World through them might know that God ſent Chriſt. For the <hi>Elect</hi> are always cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for a purpoſe, which is, to carry on the Counſel of the Will of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that as there is a peculiar calling, ſo there is likewiſe a common calling of the Goſpel, by which Salvation is attainable.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that if we are Saved, we muſt be Saved by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs according to his Word; which is in the way of our Obedience. And by our believing that Chriſt is the Son of God, we muſt Obey him as ſuch; for thoſe whoſe Wills are not brought into Subjection to Chriſt, are none of his; for all are his Servants to whom they Obey, and otherwiſe to believe in Chriſt will ſtand them in no ſtead.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that the promiſed new everlaſting Covenant is not eſtabliſht, and that it will not be till the Lord again comes, and the firſt Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, by receiving the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, had an earneſt of the inheritance for time to come.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that there are two Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38506:6"/>The firſt, when Chriſt comes to Judge the Nations in the Valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> At which time the Dead Bodies of the Saints will riſe, and <hi>Iſraels</hi> Dead Men live. And the laſt and final Judgment, is when the Sea, and Hell, and Death, deliver up their Dead.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that God by his Word, ſpeaks but to them that are under it: And when Chriſt comes, they are that World and thoſe Nations that will be condemned by it, which have not lived in Obedience to it. And it is the Sheep, and the Goats that partake of one Paſture, that then will be Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the one made Bleſſed, and the other ſent to the Fire of Hell. For the greater light they Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, the greater condemnation they fall under.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that the <hi>Elect</hi> that will be gathered from the four Winds, when the Lord again comes, ſhall be <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that the World to come, is not Heaven, but a People with whom the Lord will eſtabliſh his now promiſed new everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which Crowns Life to the Soul, and thoſe will be the World to come, which will be put into Subjection unto Chriſt, and the World without end.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that Chriſt hath cleared all from original Sin, and that all ſhall be Judged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deeds. And that there is a redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World to come, and that all innocent Children will then be cleared, and all the vertuous Heathens who have lived up to the Light which God had given them, ſo as their Conſciences excuſe them when Judged, they will then find Mercy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that it is not the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Heaven and all the Earth that will be burnt up, when the Lord comes; but it is a great ſtate of People, which in Scripture is likewiſe termed the Heavens
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38506:6"/>and Earth, and it is the Earth on which they dwell which will be burnt up, and all the works therein, ſo as never to be reſtored again.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that the Earth will be renewed, and <hi>Canaan</hi> made like the Garden of <hi>Eden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12thly.</hi> I affirm and prove, that the Glorious Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle will then be pitcht over all the Aſſemblies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo as the knowledge of the Glory of the Lord ſhall then cover the Earth, as the Waters cover the Sea.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things are of the greateſt moment in the World to be conſidered of, but whilſt the Chriſtians truſt to their Authors, and the <hi>Jews</hi> to their Talmud, it is impoſſible either ſhould come to a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP I.</hi> A full diſcovery that we are in the Gloomy and Dark day, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> terms the Night, where he ſaith,</head>
            <p>ROM. 13.12, 13, 14. <hi>The night is far ſpent, the Day is at hand: let us therefore caſt off the Works of Darkneſs, and let us put on the Armour of Light. Let us walk honeſtly as in the Day, not in Rioting and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in Strife and Envy. But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no Proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfil the Luſt thereof.</hi> Now the Night which was far ſpent then, is nigh ſpent now. For the Times being divided into three parts; Chriſt's firſt coming was at the beginning of the laſt part. And therefore the laſt part muſt needs now be near expiration, and the Day in which Chriſt will Judge the World; in which time will be <hi>the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things:</hi> The which Day is now nigh at hand,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38506:7"/>when there will not be diſorderly walking. But now is <hi>the Cloudy and Dark day,</hi> until the Lord again comes to feed his Sheep himſelf. And then <hi>will he gather them out of all Countries, and feed them upon the Mountains of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>And then will the Lord Judge between the Rams and the He-Goats,</hi> Ezek. 34.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 17.</p>
            <p>Now when the Lord firſt came, it is ſaid <hi>he came when the fulneſs of time was come,</hi> Gal. 4.4. The which was at the full time that God had appointed for his coming. It is alſo ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>God hath in theſe laſt Days ſpoken to us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom alſo he made the Worlds.</hi> Now in that the Apoſtle here ſaith, theſe laſt days, is becauſe there is other laſt, or latter Days ſpoken of in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which latter Days it is, <hi>Iſrael</hi> will receive the promiſed great and Glorious bleſſings. And he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſtinguiſhes theſe laſt Days in which the Goſpel was eſtabliſht, from thoſe that are yet to come, Iſa. 2.2. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the last days, that the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Lord's houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills; and all Nations ſhall flow unto it.</hi> Mic. 4.1. <hi>But in the last days it ſhall come to paſs, that the Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the top of the Mountains, and it ſhall be exalted above the Hills, and People ſhall flow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it,</hi> Hoſ. 3.5. <hi>Afterward ſhall the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>return, and ſeek the Lord their God, and</hi> David <hi>their King, and ſhall fear the Lord, and his goodneſs in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Days.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the Lord's ſecond coming, therefore termed theſe days the laſt days of the Goſpel inſtitution and of the Power of the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities of this World; (and the end of our time of coming in heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi>): All this will end upon the beginning of the time of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s great and glorious latter Days before quoted, but in the latter days of this time <hi>Moſes</hi> Propheſied of their falling away, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.29. According to which we ſee they have done,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38506:7"/>but after the latter Days of this time, in the time to come, which is in the latter Days alſo, and beyond the latter Days of this time, the Lord will then be merciful to his Land, and to his People. And the <hi>Nations are then to rejoyce with them, Deut.</hi> 32.43. At which time, <hi>God will render vengeance to his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and restore his People, and circumciſe their Heart and the Heart of their Seed, to love the Lord their God,</hi> Deut. 30.6. <hi>For when the Lord comes to Zion, he will turn away ungodlineſs from</hi> Jacob, Rom. 11.26. Deut. 30.3.6.8. And that there will be Days and Nights after Chriſt's ſecond coming is evident. For after Chriſt's ſecond coming, <hi>Satan is to be bound up for a Thouſand Years: and after that he is caſt into Hell to be tormented Day and Night for ever and for ever,</hi> Rev. 20.3, 10. And according to this it is faid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.4, 8. That when all the <hi>Idumean Heaven and their Hoſt ſhall be diſſolved, and rolled together a as Scrole: the which will be the day of the Lord's vengeance, and the Year of Recompences, for the Controverſie of</hi> Sion, ver. 8. Then part of the Land on which the Curſe will fall, as in the 9 and 10 Verſes, <hi>The Streams thereof ſhall be turned into Pitch, and the Duſt thereof into Brimſtone: and it ſhall not be quenched Night nor Day, the Smoke thereof ſhall go up for ever: from Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to Generation it ſhall lye wast, none ſhall paſs through it for ever and ever. But the Cormorant, and the Bittern, and ſuch like ſhall inhabit it,</hi> ver. 11. And theſe Heavens and their Hoſt, are the Heavens and Elements, unto which St. <hi>Peter</hi> had his reference, when he ſaid, <hi>The Day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night, in which the Heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the Elements melt with fervent heat, and the Earth and all the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.10. For we are to take notice that St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth not ſay all the Earth; but it is the Earth before ſpoken of by the Prophet, and all the things which are therein, which the Anger of the Lord is pronounced
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38506:8"/>againſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34. the which will ſtand as a remark of God's fore diſpleaſure againſt ſin, all the time of the world to come, as <hi>Sodom</hi> has done in this time. And therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith at the beginning of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>That he wrote to them, to stir up their minds by way of Remembrance, that they might be mindful of the Words which were ſpoken before by the holy Prophets, and of the Commands of us the Apostles,</hi> verſ. 1, 2, 3. For they required and commanded that they ſhould be mindful of the words of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>And a great State of People God generally in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls Heaven and Earth; and almoſt every Prophecy of Scripture hath at leaſt a twofold ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. The which we not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we have thereby been much in the dark: And every Name is a proper Name to that which God gives it. And if God will call two things by one Name, it as properly belongs to one as to the other. And that it is not the Material Heavens and all the Earth that is to be deſtroyed, is evident to all, from the words of the Text: Becauſe, when theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and their Hoſt, and the Earth here ſpoken of are deſtroyed, then <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be reſtored, and day and night continued; and ſucceeding Generations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.4, 5, 8, 9, 10. From whence we ſee the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Day and Night proved, both from the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>And that it is not the Material Heavens, and all the Earth, that is to be burnt up at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is further evident; for the Lord ſaith, <hi>At the end of this World he will ſend his Angels, and gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, &amp; them that work Iniquity, and cast them into a Furnace of Fire,</hi> Matth. 13.40, 41, 42. (and thoſe are the Heavens and Element that will melt as the fat of Lambs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.20.) But the Elements of Earth, Air, Fire and Water cannot melt, therefore this his Kingdom muſt be on Earth, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38506:8"/>the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> according as was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the Angel, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.31, 32, 33. For there is nothing that offendeth nor worketh Iniquity in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: but the Wicked are to be rooted out of the Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.1, 9, 10, 11, 13.20, 22, 28, 29, 34, 38. And this is to be after the ſeventh Angel ſoundeth, Then <hi>the Kingdoms of this World are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our Lord, and of his Christ, and he ſhall reign forever, and ever,</hi> Rev. 11.7. Dan. 7. Pſal. 45.7. For tho' the Diſciples and Martyrs of Jeſus, and them that overcome, have in Heaven an Inheritance reſerved for them, <hi>ready to be revealed in the last time,</hi> 1 Pet. 4, 5. For this is the Manſion or Tabernacle which the Lord goes to prepare for them; <hi>John</hi> 14.3. Which when he cometh with his Saints, he will then bring with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. For then the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> will come down out of Heaven, which is not only the Bride, the Lamb's Wife, but the glorious Tabernacle, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. Which will be placed in the Elementary Heavens, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. And ſo <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s covert over all her Aſſemblies, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5, 6. And then 'tis the Knowledge of the Glory of the Lord will cover the Earth as the Waters cover the Sea, <hi>Habba.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>But it is the Meek and the Righteous is promiſed the Earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.8, 10, 11, 29. And <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the end of this World, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.11, 12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.13. <hi>Ezek</hi> 87.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>And whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Chriſt heir of all things:</hi> Thereby he ſheweth, that what was appointed Chriſt, was not then in his poſſeſſion: And tho' Chriſt ſaid after he aroſe from the Dead, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 19. <hi>All power is given unto me in Heaven and Earth;</hi> Yet the thing given was not then poſſeſſed by him: for he was to ſit at <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right hand until his Enemies be made his Footſtool. Pſal.</hi> 110.1. The which time of the Lord's ſecond
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38506:9"/>coming. St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>the time of the Reſtitution of all things,</hi> Acts 3.21. The which is the Day St. <hi>Paul</hi> had his reference to; and relates to the time ſpoken of, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.17. When the <hi>Lord will Judge between the Rams, and He-Goats.</hi> And then as in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>That in the diſpenſation of the fulneſs of times, he might gather together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and which are on the Earth.</hi> Here it is ſaid, the Lord will come in the fulneſs of times: Thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time will be compleated, both of the Old, and this World. That is thus, the time that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, under the Law, and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, for the Lord hath given three Laws to Man as a rule for him to Steer by. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The law of Nature, <hi>2dly.</hi> The moral Law. <hi>3dly.</hi> The Goſpel inſtitution. The Law of nature is to continue in the time or World to come. And ſo likewiſe the moral Law: for then God will Circumciſe the Hearts of his People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6, 8. <hi>So as they ſhall keep all the commands of the Lord. And thou ſhalt return, and obey the voice of the Lord, and do all his Commandments which I have commanded thee this Day.</hi> In the Covenant which <hi>Moſes</hi> reherſed to them, <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.14. Chap. 30.8. For then the Lord <hi>will magnifie the Law, and make it Honourable,</hi> Iſa. 42.21. For by eſtabliſhing the promiſed New everlaſting Covenant, there will be given an inherent perfect Righteouſneſs, by which their Hearts will be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, as they ſhall thereby be made perfectly able to keep the Old Covenant. As for the Goſpel inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, the Chriſtians were but to hold that faſt till Chriſt came, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10.11. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. But the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Spirit will be forever and ever required, as to have their Wills brought in Subjection unto Chriſt, without which none can be his, neither here nor hereafter. And at Chriſt's firſt coming, <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.78. <hi>Zacharias</hi> faith <hi>the Day ſpring from on high had viſited them.</hi> And a Viſit all know is of a ſhort continuance; but he is to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38506:9"/>
               <hi>return again and Build the Tabernacle of</hi> David, <hi>which is fallen, and he will ſet up,</hi> Acts. 15.15.16.</p>
            <p>And whereas St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith to the Saints unto whom he wrote, The <hi>Darkneſs is past, and the true Light now Shineth,</hi> 1 John 2.8. He had here his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference only to them that walked in obedience to God, as in the 4th and 5th Verſes: and love to his Brother, ver. 9. For all the reſt were in Darkneſs; but this Obedience, and Love was a Ray of the true Light of that Day which is ſtill to come. And likewiſe then they had the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ſhed on them abundantly,</hi> Tit. 3.6. Which was <hi>as an earnest of their inheritance in time to come,</hi> Eph. 1.14. And theſe were thoſe of whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpoke, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. That did then partake of that <hi>marvellous Light:</hi> The which in that Day that is yet to come, they will partake and <hi>Drink abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly,</hi> Cant. 5.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19, 20, 21. For then <hi>their Sun will no more go down, for the Lord will be their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Light; and then the days of their Mourning will be ended, for then</hi> Iſrael <hi>will for evermore Drink of the River of his pleaſures,</hi> Pſal. 36.8. <hi>And know as they are known.</hi> For then <hi>God's People will partake of thoſe exceeding great and precious Promiſes, by which they will be made partakers of the divine Nature: having eſcaped the corruption that is in the World,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. For it is in the time to come, the Eternal Life will be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and therefore we are <hi>exhorted by good Works, to lay up in ſtore a good Foundation againſt the time to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.18, 19. For there is a time to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Eternity, in which the Saints, and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the true Believer will be Bleſſed; for theſe are thoſe that will have their part in the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. The which will be when the Lord comes to <hi>Judge the Nations in the Valley of</hi> Jehoſhaphat, <hi>Joel,</hi> 3.2. <hi>And reſtore his People,</hi> ver. 16, 17, 18.20, 21. And then <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be the Lord's Elect, which he will gather together <hi>when the great Trumpet is blown,</hi> Iſa. 27.13. Which will be long before, the Sea, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38506:10"/>Hell and Death deliver up their Dead. The which which be the laſt Judgment, tho in both Judgments ſome are Condemned to Eternal Puniſhment, and it is the Sinners under the Goſpel, that at the firſt fall under the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Puniſhment, being Condemned thereunto when the Lord cometh; but at the laſt Judgment the Nations are not to be Judged. For in time to come <hi>Iſrael will be all righteous: they ſhall inherit the Land for ever,</hi> and then <hi>a little one ſhall become a Thouſand, and a ſmall one a ſtrong Nation: I the Lord will haſten it in his time,</hi> Iſa. 60.21, 22. And this is the World to come that will be put in Subjection unto Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. The which will be, when the Old Heavens and Earth ſhall Periſh, which have now the ruling power: And the new Heavens and Earth take place. <hi>And then the Children of God's Servants ſhall continue, and their ſeed ſhall be eſtabliſhed before him,</hi> Pſal. 102.25, 26, 27, 28. And this is the <hi>World to come, of which the Apoſtle ſaith, we ſpeak,</hi> Heb. 2.5, 8. For that which is called a Nation, or Generation in the Old Teſtament <hi>where it is ſaid, a Seed ſhall ſerve him, and it ſhall be accounted to the Lord for a Generation,</hi> Pſal. 22.30, 31. Pſal. 24.6, 7. The ſame in the New Teſtament, is termed the World to come, and the World without end, And the Chriſtians ſince the Apoſtacy from the truth of God's Word, have never rightly underſtood this World to come, nor the Foundation thereof: Whereby great part of the Fundamental Doctrine of the Goſpel hath been overturned. And in the New Teſtament the laſt Day is ſpoken of becauſe they that are under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel will then be Judged; and the Goſpel inſtitution will then ceaſe, and the ruling Power taken out of the Hand of the People of this World: and therefore it is termed their laſt Day. But in the Old Teſtament we never read of a laſt Day, becauſe when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is again reſtored, then the Land is given them for an Everlaſting inheritance, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8. And then as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38506:10"/>the New Heavens, and the New Earth ſhall remain, ſo ſhall their Seed and their Name remain, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.22. and then 'tis that <hi>Mount Sion</hi> ſhall be made an Eternal. Excellency. But more of this hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.4, 5. <hi>But ye Brethren are not in darkneſs, that that day ſhould overtake you as a thief: ye are all the Children of the Light, and the Children of the Day; ye are not of the Night, nor of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> This he ſpeaks of them that were of the firſt Churches, which had received the Holy Ghoſt, and thereby he knew they were choſen in a more peculiar manner for that Day which is ſtill to come, as his foregoing words make clearly appear; in that he ſaith, That Day ſhould not overtake them as a Thief. And if we now in this gloomy and dark day, walk as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light, in a holy and upright Converſation, and with love to the Truth, we ſhall belong to that Day alſo. But when the Apoſtle wrote this Epiſtle, and the firſt of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> he did expect the coming of the Lord in their day; but afterwards he did declare to the contrary, for in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. he lets them underſtand, that the Day of Chriſt was not then at hand, but that there would be a falling away firſt, but nothing of a New Election afterwards to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in under the Goſpel, that being a new received notion, and Scriptureleſs.</p>
            <p>And concerning this Day which is to come, the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10. <hi>That they knew but in part, and they propheſied but in part. But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away.</hi> Now then what groſs Darkneſs muſt we lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that came out of <hi>Popery,</hi> by which was altogether loſt the right apprehenſion of that Day; for by the Pope it was condemned for a Hereſie. But St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the Church to whom he wrote, <hi>Ye do well that ye take heed as unto a Light that ſhineth in a dark place,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19. But we having loſt the right knowledge
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38506:11"/>of that day, are thereby ſtumbling on the dark Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; Every Sect ſticking to that Opinion they firſt took up with, when they came out of that darkneſs: All thinking themſelves ſo right, that they need not make any further enquiry or ſearch into the knowledge of the truth of the Scriptures. But now is the time the Lord is beginning to fulfil his Promiſe, in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4. By revealing the true meaning of his Word, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by knowledge might be increaſed; ſo as preparation may be made for the Coming of the Lord. And alſo it is ſaid, <hi>That at Evening time it ſhall he light,</hi> Zech. 14.7. And <hi>that the Viſion ſhall ſpeak, and not lie,</hi> Hab. 2.3. By which it doth clearly appear, that the Word of the Lord will be better underſtood than hitherto it hath been for theſe many hundred years.</p>
            <p>But our miſtakes concerning Election, in that we have thought our ſelves the Elect, and ſo they ſay, can never fall from Grace. And others wholly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt for Salvation, not conſidering the Conditions on which it is tendred. All theſe think they ſtand ſo ſecure, that it is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of theirs, to know whether Chriſt is coming or not: They not apprehending there are a certain Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the <hi>Jeros</hi> given to Chriſt by his Father, to be his ſtanding witneſs through the World. And that likewiſe the firſt Churches were elected, and received the Holy Ghoſt to be in them; <hi>that the World through them might know that God had ſent Chriſt;</hi> as thereby they might have ground to believe. And upon the publication of the common Salvation, was given a day of Grace by the Call of the Word, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the good motions of the Spirit of God, the which <hi>Iſrael</hi> had, till they reſiſted, in their not obeying the Commands of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.51. For they did then ſtrain at a Gnat, and ſwallow a Camel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.24. And ſo the Gentiles, <hi>till they came to have no love to the Truth,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10. Now the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38506:11"/>in theſe things, if we do not well awaken, will prove of moſt dangerous conſequence, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>For when they ſay peace and Safety, then ſudden Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cometh upon them, as Travail upon a Woman with Child.</hi> And then it is that ſuch Chriſtians will be found in Darkneſs, who have not prepared for the coming of the Lord.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>God's Love to the World.</head>
               <p>JOHN 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the VVorld, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi> That is, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very individual Perſon that believeth in Chriſt, hath a promiſe of everlaſting Life: from which words we are to take notice, that of this World or People there are ſome that will believe, and ſome that will not; but that the love of Chriſt was ſuch as to dye for all; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 2.9. <hi>That Chriſt did taſt Death for every Man.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for the Sins of the whole VVorld,</hi> 1 John, 2.2. From which Scriptures we may plainly ſee, that by Chriſt all will be cleared from original Sin, ſo as when all come to be Judged, they will be Judged accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>John</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14. And therefore in the Time or World to come there will be a Redemption for Children, and ſuch as are not wilfully Guilty. And God loving his Creatures firſt, it is that thereby it might beget in them a love to him that: dyed for them, <hi>For Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>he that loveth Father or Mother more than me, is not worthy of me,</hi> Mat. 10.37, 38. <hi>For it is a Faith that worketh by love,</hi> that is required of us, whereby our Wills and Affections muſt be brought into Subjection unto Chriſt. The which is the Faith unto which the promiſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life is annext.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38506:12"/>
               <p>For that which Chriſt would have us believe, is, That Salvation is to be had by him according to his Word, that is, by <hi>taking his Yoke upon them,</hi> and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obedience to him; And to <hi>remain faithful to the Death,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt will give them a Crown of Life,</hi> Rev. 2.10. Whoſoever thus believeth in Chriſt, ſhall be ſaved with an everlaſting Salvation; for theſe are the Words of Chriſt, and we are to expect his coming; and his Kingdom according as it is declared in his Word: But whoſoever believeth not what God and Chriſt hath declared, cannot be ſaid to believe in them.</p>
               <p>And by our believing that Chriſt is the Son of God, thereby is required, we ſhould obey him as ſuch: But whoſoever will oppoſe the Truth, and believe what Man ſays, rather than God, becauſe it more ſuits to their carnal inclinations, ſuch cannot be ſaid to obey God, or believe in him; but rather in cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed Fables.</p>
               <p>But the Sinner upon his reſignation of himſelf to Chriſt, is thereby ſaved <hi>from his Sins which are paſt, Rom.</hi> 3.25. And by his continuance in well doing, he ſhall be ſaved with an everlaſting Salvation: and for Sins of ignorance, and Sins of ſurpriſal, Chriſt remains an Advocate. But let all take care of wilful and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Sins, for they cauſe God to withdraw himſelf; For which cauſe God left <hi>Iſrael to Blindneſs;</hi> and the <hi>Gentile Chriſtians to deluſions,</hi> when they came <hi>to have no love to the Truth, but took pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10. And now the Chriſtians had beſt take care they are not found to have no love to the Truth, leſt thereby they work their overthrow. But the Chriſtians by their miſtaken notions are for the moſt part upon a wrong Foundation, whereby they are in the Snare, according to the Word of the Lord, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Chap. 24.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38506:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> made the Figures or Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of two Nations, or two ſeveral Sorts of People.</head>
               <p>GEN. 25.22, 23. <hi>Rebeckah enquired of the Lord concerning the Strugling of the Children in her Womb.</hi> ver. 23. <hi>And the Lord ſaid to her, two Nations are in thy Womb, and two manner of People ſhall be ſeparated from thy Bowels, and the one People ſhall be Stronger than the other People, and the Elder ſhall ſerve the Younger.</hi> We are here to take notice, that God doth not here ſay that he hated <hi>Eſau;</hi> neither that the Elder Brother ſhould ſerve the Younger; but it is ſaid of the Elder People, that they ſhould ſerve the Younger, and it is the Younger People that ſhall be Stronger than the Elder. For God made theſe two Brethren the Figures of two Nations, or the two Worlds of People, <hi>Eſau</hi> of this World, and <hi>Jacob</hi> of that which is to come. And this God determined before the Children had done Good or Evil: That the Elder People or Nation, ſhould ſerve the Younger. But God had not here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined hatred to either, nor ſervitude to the Elder Brother, unto whom God firſt gave the Preheminence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7. And <hi>Jacob,</hi> tho' he got from <hi>Eſau</hi> the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and Bleſſing as to his Seed, yet he went not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to take it from <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Perſon, for <hi>Jacob</hi> termed <hi>him his Lord</hi> Eſau, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.18. <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.8.13, 14.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.26. <hi>That Jacob's Hand took hold of Eſan's Heel:</hi> Thereby ſhewing, that the full Power of the Younger World will come in upon the going off of the Power of the Elder World of People: and that which is called a Nation, People or Generation, in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.28, 29, 30, 31. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.26, 27, 28. is called the World to come in the New, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. And theſe Younger Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38506:13"/>muſt needs be the Stronger People, <hi>For they will be all Righteous,</hi> Iſa. 60.21. <hi>They ſhall teach no more every Man his Neighbour and his Brother, for they ſhall be all taught of God,</hi> Jer. 31.34. And then it is <hi>they will walk in the Statutes of the Lord, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and do them,</hi> Ezek. 36.24, 25, 26, 27. Deut. 30.6. Jer. 32.39, 40, 41. <hi>And they will drink of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of his Pleaſures,</hi> Pſal. 36.8. And that <hi>abundantly,</hi> Cant. 5.1. And they <hi>will live to the Age of a Tree,</hi> Iſa. 65.22. <hi>And the Beaſt of the Field, and the Fowls of Heaven, and all other Creatures will be ſubject to them.</hi> Hoſ. 2.18. Eze. 34.25. <hi>And the Lord will make with them the Promiſed new everlaſting Covenant,</hi> Jer. 32.41, 42. <hi>which is the Covenant of Peace,</hi> Ezek. 34.35. <hi>And reſt in his love, and rejoyce over them,</hi> Zeph. 3.17. <hi>And then they ſhall not ſay I am Sick,</hi> Iſa. 33.24. <hi>And ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away,</hi> Iſa. 35.10. <hi>And the Lord will be Prince amongſt them,</hi> Ezek. 34.24, 25. <hi>And then the weak will be as the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>will be as God,</hi> Zechariah, Chap. 12.8. <hi>And then their ſeed ſhall be known amongſt the Gentiles, and their off ſpring among the People, Iſa.</hi> 61.9, 10, 11. <hi>And the Gentiles ſhall ſee thy righteouſneſs, and all Kings thy Glory: Thou ſhalt alſo be a Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord, and a Royal Diadem in the hand of thy God, Iſa.</hi> 62.2, 3. Here is ſufficient proof that theſe Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er People will be abundantly ſtronger than the Elder People: and then this Younger People, which are the Ages to come, become thus Bleſſed: then God will ſhew forth the exceeding Riches of his Grace to the Apoſtles, and Saints, and Martyrs of Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. Who then will have their place in the Glorious Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle which the Lord will pitch, and not Man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.2. which Tabernacle will be <hi>Iſrael's</hi> covert, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.6. From whence the Lord with his raiſed Saints, will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend and deſcend to the real <hi>Mount Sion:</hi> as the Lord
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38506:13"/>formlery did from the Cloudy Pillar to the Tabernacle, as I have elſewhere at large proved.</p>
               <p>And in time to come, the Nations are given to be Servants to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> For the Lord ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. <hi>The Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve thee, ſhall periſh: yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted.</hi> And then it is that the Elder People, World, or Nation are to ſerve the Younger, according as God by his Word has declared.</p>
               <p>But thus far <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> did repreſent the two Nations, or two Worlds of People in this time, in their own Perſons. For as <hi>Eſan</hi> was hairy all over, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.25. which ſignifies roughneſs or an unſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; And <hi>Eſau</hi> was therein like the conſtitution of this World of People, as to their mind and practice; And <hi>Eſau</hi> got his food by Hunting; ſo this World Hunts and Labours for their food. But <hi>Jacob</hi> was a ſmooth Man, repreſenting the Time or World to come, in which time there will be Smoothneſs and calmneſs, with all ſerenity; and Proviſion in abundance without Hunting for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Servitude.</head>
               <p>BUt as for the Servitude the Lord had determined for the Elder World, before the Children had done good or evil: In that Servitude they will be more Bleſſed than ever they would have been without it. For God promiſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> that in him <hi>all the Families of the Earth ſhould be Bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 12.3. Gen. 18.18. Gen. 22.17, 18. Gen. 26.4. Which is by Chriſt, and partly made good at Chriſt's firſt coming by the publication of the Goſpel, by which many of the Nations embraced the Faith, by laying hold of the common Salvation wich is therein tendred, <hi>Jude</hi> 2. <hi>For Chriſt taſted Death for every Man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. Heb. 5.9. John 3.16. 1 John 2.2. In which common Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, I neither mean the elect remnant that was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38506:14"/>choſen from among <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto whom Chriſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be with to the end of the World: Nor the People that God at the firſt viſiting the Gentiles, did take out from among them for his Name, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.14. The which People then received the Holy Ghoſt to be in them, that they might be a light to the World: And that the World through them might believe or know that God had ſent Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.23. That thereby the Nations might take hold of the offered Mercy, which accordingly they did, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.6. and ſo became the Seed of <hi>Abraham<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And whilſt they walkt in the ſtops of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Rom. 4.12. They were heirs to <hi>Iſraels</hi> promiſes: and that by Chriſt, who was of the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah; And ſet forth as a propitiation through Faith in his Blood for the remiſſion of Sins that are paſt, Rom.</hi> 3.25. to all them that then believed according to the tender of his Grace. Therefore they then concluded upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the Goſpel, or of a Sinners reſigning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Chriſt to ſerve him, that a Man was juſtified by Faith, without the deeds of the Law, Chap. 3.26, 27, 28. But in the Faith that they were to believe, were included the deeds of the Law: For it is required they ſhould walk according to it, for they are to be Judged by it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. For the Lord will render to every Man according to his deeds, when Judged. Chap. 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>And Chriſt is become the Author of eternal Salvation to all them that obey him,</hi> Heb 5.9. And walk before God with a perfect Heart, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. And like him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the promiſed Reward in the way of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And whilſt the Gentiles that had embrac'd the Faith walk'd in his ſteps, they were Heirs to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: and it is ſuch will be partakers of the Glory promiſed in time to come. The which time, will be the time of Chriſt's Kingdom; And then all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the Earth will be Bleſſed in <hi>Abraham</hi> and his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38506:14"/>Seed. For after the Lord has avenged himſelf of his Enemies; which Enemies are thoſe who regard not the Counſel of the Lord, and will have none of his Reproof; againſt theſe he will ſpend his Arrows. And <hi>then God calls to the Nations to rejoyce with his People,</hi> Deut. 32.42, 43. For then all the Nations that are given to be <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Servants, will have cauſe to rejoice, in that they will then be made bleſſed thereby, when all thoſe of <hi>Mount-Seir</hi> and <hi>Idumea,</hi> who through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of the Promiſe made to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> boaſt themſelves, and deny the Time or World to come, in which the Lord will make his Promiſes good. And through Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs of this preſent evil world, they, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſell their Birth-right for this world's Morſel: And it is theſe <hi>Edomites ſhall be made deſolate, when the whole Earth rejoyceth,</hi> Ezek. 35.12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Eſau</hi> was but termed <hi>Edom,</hi> upon the deſiring the Pottage; for which Pottage be ſold his Birth-right, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.31, 32, 33. As not believing the Promiſes which God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as relating to this time, nor that which is to come; unto which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Bleſſedneſs belongs. For if he had believed the Promiſes, he would not have ſaid, <hi>If I dye for Hunger, what profit ſhall this Birth-right do me?</hi> And it was through Unbelief of a future ſlate, made him unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to encounter with Difficulties; and therefore ſold his Birth-right, to which the Bleſſing was annext: <hi>For which, afterward when he would have inherited the Bleſſing, he was rejected,</hi> Heb. 12.17. And had not <hi>Jacob</hi> known the advantage that was to be had by the Birth-right, he would not have deſired it from him.</p>
               <p>For had not the Bleſſing gone with the Birth-right, <hi>Jacob</hi> had been in a far better condition without it, for then he had purchaſed the Servitude with the Birth-right: But <hi>Iſaac, Rebecca,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> well knew that it was the Elder People, Nation, or World, that was to ſerve the Younger. And as <hi>Eſau</hi> through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38506:15"/>diſinherited himſelf; ſo the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> by their diſobedience and unbelief, have in this time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inherited themſelves. Yet in the time to come, the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> will have the promiſed Bleſſing, with whom the true Believer will come in Heir with.</p>
               <p>And in this time, the Covenant which God made with the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> was ſuch, that others might take hold of it; Strangers as well as <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 29.14, 15. So that the natural ſeed of <hi>Eſau</hi> were not excluded from it; as many as would come in, according to the condition of the Covenant, might be Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in time to come. And <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Seed knowing the Covenant of the Lord, and they not joining with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the true Worſhip, they were more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable than the reſt of the Nations. For the true God, was the God of their Fathers. But in the time to come, the unborn Poſterity of <hi>Eſau,</hi> then cannot come in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Neither any of this World can partake of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Promiſes in time to come, but thoſe that come in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Jacob's <hi>Bleſſing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Bleſſing wherewith <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed <hi>Jacob,</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to him and his Seed, the which had not only Reference to this Time, or World, but much more to that which is to come. For unto him he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Words of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 12.3. <hi>I will bleſs them that bleſs thee, and curſe him that curſeth thee.</hi> For in the Bleſſing, <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid to <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 28.29. <hi>God give thee of the Dew of Heaven, and the Fatneſs of the Earth, and plenty of Corn and Wine. Let People ſerve thee, and Nations bow down to thee; be Lord over thy Brethren, and let thy Mother's Sons bow down to thee; curſed be every one that curſeth thee, and bleſſed be he that bleſſeth thee.</hi> This Bleſſing, as I ſaid before, muſt needs have its chief reference to the Generations of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Children in time to come,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38506:15"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.18, 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.30, 31. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.5, 6, 7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39, 40, 41.</p>
               <p>But as to the Bleſſing with which <hi>Iſaac</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Eſau</hi> and his Seed, in which he had therein his reference to the time of this World, and not to the time of that which is to come, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.39, 40. <hi>For</hi> Iſaac <hi>his Father ſaid, behold thy dwelling ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll be the fatneſs of the Earth, and the dew of Heaven from above. And by thy Sword ſhalt thou live, and ſhalt ſerve thy Brother: and it ſhall come to paſs when thou ſhalt have the dominion, that thou ſhalt break his Yoke from off thy Neck.</hi> The which Yoke was to be broken off in this time, according as we ſee it has been. But in time to come, it cannot be, <hi>For then the Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſhall periſh: yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly wasted,</hi> Iſa. 60.12. <hi>For then no Weapon formed againſt</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>ſhall proſper,</hi> Iſa. 54.17. <hi>And God ſayeth to them,</hi> verſ. 7.8. <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great Mercies will I gather thee: In a little wrath I hid my face from thee, for a moment; but with everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer.</hi> For as God hath ſworn <hi>that the Waters of</hi> Noah <hi>ſhould no more go over the Earth; ſo hath he ſworn that he would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee,</hi> verſ. 9. The which is when again reconciled.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Eſau</hi> weeping ſo bitterly for the loſs of the Bleſſing; that <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid nothing to him concerning the time to come, but rather choſe to comfort him concerning this time, in which he ſhould break his Brother's Yoke from off him.</p>
               <p>But all in this time, that come in Heirs with <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> by <hi>Abraham's</hi> Faith, become the Seed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And ſo the unbelievers through their unbelief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Seed of <hi>Eſau</hi> or <hi>Edom:</hi> For now all being reckoned as <hi>Eſau</hi> or <hi>Edom</hi> that know the Will of God, and will not live in obedience to it, through unbelief of the promiſes: and ſo ſuch part with the Glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38506:16"/>for this Worlds morſel, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> for which he was termed prophane, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16, 17. But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the promiſed reward, carried the worthies of Old through all difficulties, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.12. So as they hoped againſt hope, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did for his promiſed Son, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18. So the Chriſtians ſhould have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hoping for the return of the Lord according to the promiſes in the Old and New Teſtament; both being given as Ground to Build our Faith upon. But when the Gentile Chriſtians thought the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed his coming, then they began to grow weary of waiting for the return of the Lord, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the promiſes, that will be made good by him in time to come. The which when they belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not, they reſolved to make as much advantage of the preſent time as they could. And ſo all ſuch part with the promiſed reward for this Worlds morſel; And therefore are termed, <hi>Edom, Mount Seir, and all Idumea,</hi> Ezek. 35.12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh Eſau</hi> or <hi>Edom,</hi> hath been more cruel &amp; inveterate to the Saints and People of God, and eſpecially the evil Servant, that beat his Fellow Servants, than ever the <hi>Eſau</hi> that came of the Loyns of <hi>Jacob</hi> was, or could be. And it was againſt this <hi>Eſau,</hi> which the Lord declares his hatred to in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy:</hi> That being a Propheſie that related to the time to come. And therefore the Lord ſpeaking of things that are to come, as tho' they were already done, ſaith, Chap. 1.3. <hi>And I hated</hi> Eſau, <hi>and laid his Mountains, and his Heritage waſt, for the Dragons of the Wilderneſs.</hi> This is the ſame <hi>Edom</hi> Propheſied of, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 35.15. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.4, 5, 6. And it is the ſame People ſpoke of, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16. And in ſeveral other places, which will be then Judged; and theſe People of <hi>Eſau,</hi> will be deſtroyed when the Lord comes again: and then their Mountains will be laid waſt for the Dragons of the Wilderneſs. And ſome part of it will remain as burning Lakes, as a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38506:16"/>remark of God's ſore diſpleaſure againſt Sin. For which they are termed the People of God's curſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.5.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.5, 6.</p>
               <p>But again, concerning this <hi>Edom</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Whereas</hi> Edom <hi>ſaith, we are impoveriſhed, but we will return and build the deſolate Places: Thus ſaith the Lord of Hosts, they ſhall build, but I will throw down: and they ſhall call them the border of Wickedneſs, and the People againſt whom the Lord hath indignation for ever.</hi> This is a Propheſie ſpoken of the <hi>ever</hi> of the time to come: And then as in the 5 verſ. <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Eyes ſhall ſee, and they ſhall ſay, the Lord will be magnified from the Borders of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay, how can the <hi>Edomites</hi> after they are deſtroyed, and their Mountains laid waſt, ſay they will return and Build their deſolate places if this in the 4th verſ. be ſpoken for the time to come?</p>
               <p>This is ſpoken of the Children of this <hi>Eſau</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> which when the Lord comes will be ſpared, when their Parents for their unbelief and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will be cut off, for the Lord ſaith, <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.10. There ſpeaking of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and of the Lord's <hi>making of him bare,</hi> ſaith in the 11 verſ. <hi>Leave thy Fatherleſs Children, I will preſerve them alive, and let thy Widows trust in me.</hi> Theſe Widows do plainly appear to be thoſe that are deceived by falſe Teachers, but not otherwiſe wilfully Wicked: For when the Rams and He-Goats are Judged, that have one Paſture to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of; 'Tis the He-Goats for treading down the good Paſtures and fouling of the deep Waters will then be Condemned, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.10, 17, 18. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then their Widows are ſpared. And theſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which the Lord ſaith he will preſerve alive. God declares how he will diſpoſe of them, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.8. Which is, that they <hi>ſhall be ſold to the</hi> Sabeans: from whence when they are again multiplyed, they may return to Build their diſolate Places. But God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38506:17"/>declared, they ſhould lie waſt: therefore they diſobey in their returning to Build them, and they proving diſobedient as well as their Predeceſſors, are called <hi>the Border of Wickedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as God loved <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he obeyed the voice of God, and kept his charge, his Commandments, his Statutes, and his Laws, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.4, 5. Therefore God made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, thoſe great and Bleſſed promiſes for the time to come: And for the wickedneſs of this <hi>Eſau</hi>-Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God hath more diſregard to their Offspring in time to come, than to all the reſt of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For Chriſt in this time having broken down the partion-wall between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. So as theſe might have come in to the everlaſting inheritance in time to come, until they came to have no love to the Truth, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 10, 11. And the firſt Chriſtians embraced the true Faith, but ſome Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years after, they fell from the Truth, and trauſgreſſed the Laws, changed the Ordinances, and broke the everlaſting Covenant. Therefore where this Offenc is found, <hi>the Curſe devoureth the Earth, and they that dwell therein are deſolate,</hi> Iſa. 24.5, 6. And for theſe things it is, that God's ſore diſpleaſure will be againſt them. For the moral Law is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant between God and Man: And by eſtabliſhing the promiſed New everlaſting Covenant, there will be given an inherent perfect Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by which they ſhall be enabled perfectly to keep the Old, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6, 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.21. But in this time it is required that we ſhould walk blameleſly in them, as <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.6. <hi>And to have kept the Ordinances as they were delivered,</hi> as the firſt Churches did, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. And ſeveral Generations; Till ſuch time they began to think the Lord delayed his coming, ſo grew weary to wait on the Lord in his way, and for his time, for the performance of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38506:17"/>his Promiſes: And when they came to have no Love to the Truth, then they changed the Laws, and brake the Everlaſting Covenant. The which is, to love the Lord God with all their Heart, and with all their Soul; and do Equity to their Neighbour, and to have ſerved God according to his own Inſtitution. But the forementioned doing otherwiſe, therefore are Condemned, for Man in this time is left to his own free will. <hi>For when the Beaſt thought or deſired to change times or laws, it was given into his Hands,</hi> Dan. 7.25. And the common tender of God's grace, is to all that are athirſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. And it is thoſe that are <hi>Condemned at Judgment, that hate knowledge, and will not chuſe the counſel of the Lord,</hi> Pro. 1 29, 30. And tho' none by their willing or running, can make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Elected or fore-choſen: Nor when the Maſter of the Houſe is riſen up to Judgment, then none by their willing or running can find admittance into the Wedding Supper, but thoſe of the Chriſtians that are afore prepared: And thoſe Chriſtians that are not, they do not then only exclude themſelves, but their unborn Poſterity. For then the Mercy, or bleſſing will according to the promiſe, which is to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the Lord <hi>comes again to Sion,</hi> Rom. 11 26, 27. And God knowing the great diſadvantage it would be to the Chriſtians, and their offspring, for that Day to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them at unawares; Therefore hath declared that <hi>at the time of the end, knowledge ſhould be increaſed,</hi> Dan. 12.4. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat at Evening time it ſhould be Light,</hi> Zach. 14 7. <hi>And that at the end of the time, the Viſion ſhall ſpeak, and not lye: tho it tarry, wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come,</hi> Hab. 2.3. For great is the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage both to <hi>Jew,</hi> and to <hi>Gentile,</hi> to underſtand aright the time that is to come. For tho' the great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Mercy then belongs to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet the Wicked amongſt them muſt expect to fall before the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant is eſtabliſht: as they did formerly on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38506:18"/>the other ſide of the River <hi>Jordan.</hi> Therefore in this time to both the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> there is a race ſet, that thoſe that will, may run for the Prize. And now eſpecially, the Glory being ſo near, let every thinking Soul, <hi>So run, as they may obtain,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.23. 24, 25, 26, 27. But thoſe that perſiſt in unbelief, and ſtill ſay, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his Coming,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.4. <hi>To reſtore all things</hi> as you ſay, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21. Such muſt expect to fall under the ſevere Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Wherefore God hated <hi>Eſau</hi> or <hi>Edom.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And God ſpeaking concerning this time to come, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.3. <hi>That he loved</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hated</hi> Eſau; is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Younger Generation that then comes in of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> tho' their Predeceſſors that were under the Law, were formerly Wicked, yet the Lord for his Oaths ſake will make his promiſe good to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in time to come. And then in the day of the Lord's power, he will make his People a willing People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. As he did upon the eſtabliſhing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, when he then took out from among the Gentiles a People for his Name, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.15. For a Propheſie of Scripture hath more than a private tendency, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. And this in the fore-cited Pſalm, hath it's chief reference to the time to come: When <hi>Iſrael ſhall be all Righteous and inherit the Land for ever,</hi> Iſa. 60.21. And then it is the <hi>Lord will ordain Peace for them: And work all their works in them,</hi> Iſa. 26.12. And then it is, the Lord <hi>will not be wroth with them, nor rebuke them any more,</hi> Iſa. 54.9. Then it is they will <hi>be of one Heart and one Way,</hi> Jer. 32.39. And then <hi>they ſhall dwell in Peaceable habitations, and in ſure dwellings, and in quiet resting Places,</hi> Iſa. 32.18. And then it is, <hi>that his Elect ſhall long injoy the work of their Hands, Iſa.</hi> 65.22. And then it is, <hi>The Lord will plant them, that they may dwell in a Place of their own, and move no more
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38506:18"/>Neither ſhall the Children of Wickedneſs afflict them any were,</hi> 2 Sam. 7.10. And then it is, <hi>That God ſhall cauſe them that come of</hi> Jacob <hi>to take Root,</hi> Iſa. 27.6. And then it is, <hi>God will rest in his love,</hi> Zeph. 3.17. For then the Lord will ſecure them to himſelf for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, by eſtabliſhing the now promiſed New ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9. <hi>And this will be all done of Grace and Mercy, for the promiſe ſake God made to their</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who <hi>obeyed the voice of the Lord, and kept his Charge, his Commandments, his Statutes, and his Laws,</hi> Gen. 26.5.</p>
               <p>At which time the Young Offspring of <hi>Edom,</hi> their Mountains are then laid waſt for the Sins of their Parents; And they ſold to be Servants to them that are Servants to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And they as the reſt of the Nations, are left to their own free-will, which for the Thouſand Years that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is bound, they may probably keep the Station in which God had placed them: But when Satan is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain looſed, he readily deceives them; they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to ſubmit to the portion that God hath allotted them. By which God's indignation will be ſhewed againſt them, becauſe they were of the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Wickedneſs. And Satan will then inſnare ſome other of the Nations with them, as many as he can draw to Covet and evil Covetouſneſs; And then God leaves them to the Devil's deluſion, to go up to plunder <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for which they will be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.12, 22. Whilſt the other Nations that are likewiſe then left to their own free will; yet they not being willing to diſobey God, could not be drawn to the coveting of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s wealth; as to Plunder and Rebel againſt them, unto whom God had given the Sovereignty. Thus God will be juſtified by them who then remain undeceived; that the others might have ſtood, if they would have reſiſted the Devils
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38506:19"/>Temptations. And after Satan is caſt into the Fire of Hell for ever and ever, thoſe People and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that will obey the Lord, may; and thoſe that will not, for want of Rain, will dwindle away, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.17. And the others being not Fruitful, the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will decreaſe, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to the Word of the Lord <hi>will Bloſſom and Bud, and fill the face of the World with Fruit,</hi> Iſa. 27.6. And then it is <hi>a little one ſhall become a Thouſand, and a ſmall one a strong Nation: The Lord will haſten it in his time,</hi> Iſa. 60.22. And theſe are the World to come, and the World that will never be Judged: Becauſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> is then betroth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord for ever, in loving-kindneſs and in Mercy, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. And therefore fore at the laſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the Sea, and Hell, and Death deliver up their Dead, there is none of the Nations Judged, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13. For this World to come, is World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. For the Lord ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.22. As the new Heavens, and the new Earth which I will make, ſhall remain before me, ſaith the Lord, ſo ſhall your Seed and your Name remain.</p>
               <p>The which New Heavens and Earth which God will make, is to be comprehended under a two or threefold Head, for the Lord with the raiſed Saints, will be a Heaven; for in Scripture a ruling power is a Heaven, as I have already proved; and when the Lord comes with his Saints to take to himſelf his own great Power and Reign, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, 17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, 7, 15. Then there is a new Heaven, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they are made Plants Righteouſneſs, at which time they will be all Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. Then they will be the Earth, wherein dwells Righteouſneſs, and theſe will be the new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Earth that will take place upon the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing away of the Old, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. <hi>2dly,</hi> the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Manſion, which the Lord is gone to prepare for his Saints, he will then bring with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.3.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38506:19"/>The which will then be a new Heaven and a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cle of Covert, over all the Aſſemblies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Es. 4.5, 6. And then their Land will be like the Garden of <hi>Eden, Ezek.</hi> 36.35. And then it will be a new Earth, and ſo a new Heavens and new Earth, and the other part of the Earth will be renewed and made Fruitful, and the Darks and Clouds diſperſed, thereby will appear a new Face put upon all things, is <hi>Rev.</hi> What is here hinted as to the Heavens and Earth, is at large proved in my Book, of the <hi>Figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Speeches.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Kingdom of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>David.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> were the Figures or Repreſentatives of the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. The Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> the Figure of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this World, who have a day of Grace put into their Hands: But for his diſobedience, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was taken from him.</p>
               <p>And <hi>David</hi> was the lively Repreſentative of the Kingdom that is to come: The which Kingdom, the Lord commanded us Daily to pray for. Which Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical Kingdom, <hi>David</hi> long waited for after he had the promiſe of it, and he ſtood in all his Tryals, till he received the Crown. For which God made with him an everlaſting Covenant, and ſure in that he would never take his loving Kindneſs from him nor his Son, as he did from <hi>Saul.</hi> And therefore it was termed the ſure Mercies of <hi>David:</hi> After which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> Sinned, as to the matter of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> for which God hurled him off from his Throne: and as he ſaith, broke all his Bones; for thoſe that are in this time without Chaſtiſement, are Baſtards and not Sons, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8. But God would not take the Kingdom
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38506:20"/>from him, becauſe of the Oath that he had made him, with the promiſe to his Seed.</p>
               <p>But the common tender of his Grace is now to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that is a thirſt, that they may freely come and Eat that which is Good, but their Souls muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in fatneſs, and this God will be Judge of, for we muſt be brought to Judgment, before we ſhall be thought meet to be inheritors with the Saints in Light, as to partake of the ſure Mercies of <hi>David, Iſa.</hi> 55.4, 5.</p>
               <p>And as the Hiſtorical part of the Bible gives us an account that in <hi>David</hi>'s time, the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> grew Weaker and Weaker, and the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> Stronger, and Stronger; So the Prophetical part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that in time to come, the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> will gorw Weaker and Weaker, and the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> grow Stronger and Stronger. As in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.6. God then ſhall cauſe them of <hi>Jacob</hi> to take Root, <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall Bloſſom and Bud, and fill the Face of the World with Fruit; and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.22. <hi>A little one ſhall become a Thouſand, and a ſmall one a ſtrong Nation: I the Lord will haſten it in his time.</hi> For this is not to be untill the time to come: At which time, the Younger Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Strength, will thus wonderfully ſurpaſs the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; And then his People alſo ſhall be all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they ſhall inherit the Land for ever, the Branch of my Planting, the work of my Hands that I may be Glorified. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> is comprehended under a Fourfold Head: The which belief was account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him for Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, that God called him to forſake his Country, and Kindred, and his Fathers Houſe. <hi>And God ſaid, I will give thee the Land, Gen.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.4.5. And upon this condition, we have Eternal Life
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38506:20"/>given us, if we will forſake the Vanities of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evil World, and take up their Croſs, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37, 38, 39. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. And like <hi>Abraham</hi> walk with God with a perfect Heart, the which God required or him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. The which is to be ſincere and upright.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly. Abraham</hi> believed the promiſe that God made to him in the gift of a Son by <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife: And he was in continual expectation of the gift of this Son, even till Old Age; and then hoped againſt hope, Judging him Faithful that had promiſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18, 21. So the Chriſtians ſhould have waited for the coming of the Lord to Judge and Reign, and Reſtore all things, according as it is declared by St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.21. And as he ſaith alſo, by all the Holy Prophets ſince the World began.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly. Abraham</hi> believed the Judge of all the World would do right, And not ſlay the Righteous with the Wicked, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. For his belief was that every one be ſhould Judged, as their deeds require ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the World of the Lord. 'That the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Righteous ſhall be upon him, and the Wickedneſs of the Wicked ſhall be upon him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20. And not that God had reprobated any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had offended, as ſome ignorantly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly. Abraham</hi>'s Faith was ſuch, that he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with the deſire of his Heart, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of his Eyes, when God required it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſo freely offered up his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> for a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; ſtill Believing that God could by him make his Promiſe good, for which thing God was ſo well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him that God made to him thoſe great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p>But how have the Chriſtians retain'd this Faith when they are ſo far out as to theſe Heads? All as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38506:21"/>to ſome of theſe Heads, and ſome to all of them: yet think like them of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> That they ſtand in need of nothing, not knowing that they are Poor, Blind and Naked, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. And if they do not with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Heart, ask of the Lord Eye-Salve, that they may ſee the great Truth in his Word, which he hath now diſcovered, and made plain according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and at his own time, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4. The ſhame of their Nakedneſs will quickly appear. And then all the imaginary Faith of Man's forging will be like ſo many Fig leaves; And all their imagin'd Elections will then ſtand them in no Stead: And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that truſt to their Baptiſmal Covenant, tho' they perform not the Conditions of it, yet think they ſhall be ſaved by it. Whereby they do but high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their Condemnation; and by which means the Nations are involved in falſe Oaths, both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Baptized and their Sureties, they promiſing that which they do not, neither can perform.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Papiſt</hi> believe in their Prieſt's Pardons: ſo that moſt have loſt the Grounds of a true Faith, by falſe imaginary fictions. And ſo the Gentile Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are moſt of them in a deplorable condition. I deſire none to be offended, becauſe I ſpeak thus plain; it is by reaſon their Souls lye at Stake; for when the Lord comes, we cannot ſtand upon a Sandy Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but it is he that has done the will of God ſhall be Rewarded. <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Reference to <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Rebeckah.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw St. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. He having there in his Alluſion to <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> hath therein his reference to Chriſt's firſt and ſecond coming, and to the ſeveral Elections that were and are to be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in at thoſe times according to the Promiſe: For he ſaith in verſ. 6. <hi>They are not all</hi> Iſrael <hi>which are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38506:21"/>Iſrael,</hi> and in verſ. 7. <hi>Neither becauſe they are the Seed of</hi> Abraham <hi>are they all Children, but in</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy Seed be called,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> came of the Loins of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the Fleſh, yet his Son ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe: And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 8 <hi>They which are the Children of the Fleſh are not the Children of God; but the Children of the promiſe are accounted for the Seed;</hi> And all that live not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of the Fleſh, but according to the Spirit, are Heirs according to promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. For it is ſuch <hi>ſhall live in his Holy Hill,</hi> and unto ſuch as obey Chriſt, <hi>he will be the Author of Eternal Salvation</hi> to them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. But St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath here his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar reference to them that were and are to be call'd in according to promiſe, at the ſet time appointed. And therefore he firſt alludeth to <hi>Sarah,</hi> in verſ. 9. In which he hath a reference to Chriſt' firſt coming, which was according to promiſe, at which ſet time there was ſome call'd in both of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> by a peculiar calling, and that according to promiſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.14. And that not for any works of Righteouſneſs which they had then done: but according to his Mercy he ſaved them. For they were brought out of Idolatry and Heatheniſm, and therefore could not be ſaved for the works of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs that they had then done. <hi>But whom God did foreknow, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the image of his Son,</hi> Rom. 8.29. <hi>For they were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to believe, but to ſuffer for his Sake;</hi> And to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to all that would lay hold of the offered Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and by Faith and Patience in continuance in well doing, they might inherit the Promiſes. But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle foreſeeing that the Gentiles that came in upon the common Salvation, would not long retain this Faith, as ſo to tread in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to remain the Children of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goes on, and ſaith in the 10 verſ. <hi>Not only
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38506:22"/>this, but when</hi> Rebeckah <hi>had conceived by one, even our Father</hi> Iſaac: <hi>For the Children being not then Born, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having done good or evil, that the purpoſe of God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth, it was ſaid unto her, the Elder ſhall ſerve the Younger.</hi> Here the Apoſtle hath his whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the time or World to come, unto which God hath determined the Glory, that the Elder. People ſhould ſerve the Younger, <hi>that the purpoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Election might stand.</hi> That according to promiſe at the appointed time when the <hi>Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain comes to Sion, he will turn away ungodlineſs from</hi> Jacob, Rom: 11.25, 26, 27, 28. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16. And it is then the Elder People, Nation, or World ſhall ſerve the Younger. The which the foreſaid two Brothers were made the Repreſentatives of. But St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes no expoſition on the Servitude, becauſe it hath it's reference to the Heathen in time to come; and it is in the time to come that <hi>Iſrael</hi> will inherit the promiſes: though not the Seed according to the Fleſh, altho they come of the Loyns of their Fathers. For then the Lord will circumciſe their Hearts, and the Heart of their Seed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6, 8. So as then they will love and obey the Lord: which in this time through the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fleſh, and Sinful inclinations of the mind, they did not obey him. But in this time to come, then it is their Righteouſneſs is of the Lord, when they are made thus perfectly Righteous, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13, 14, 17. And whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, Rom, 9.22. <hi>As it is written,</hi> Jacob <hi>have I loved, and</hi> Eſau <hi>have I hated.</hi> Now the Apoſtle here having his alluſion to the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> in time to come, has likewiſe here his reference to the Seed of <hi>Eſau</hi> in time to come. And whereas he ſaith, as it is written, therein he includes the <hi>Eſau</hi> or <hi>Edom,</hi> whoſe Mountains and Heritage will then be laid waſt in time to come, for the Sins
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38506:22"/>of their Parents: for whoſe diſobedience God will have leſs regard to them, than to any other. For tho' the Children in time to come are alike Guiltleſs, yet the Lord then will make great difference among them, according as he hath declared in his Word, Iſa. 60.12. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.8. And it is the Mountains of this latter <hi>Eſau</hi> that will then be laid waſt for the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of the Wilderneſs: And then it is that God ſhews more diſlike or hatred to their Seed, than to any other. For then it is God gives their Young off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring to be Servants to them, that are Servants to Iſrael, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.8. And in time to come becauſe they were the Offspring of the Wicked, and for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to Build their deſolate Places, they are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et the Borders of Wickedneſs: And the People againſt whom the Lord hath indignaiton for ever, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.4. Which ever, is the ever of the time to come. <hi>This time being reckoned one ever, and the time to come another ever, And God hath declared that the Wicked ſhall be cut off from the Earth,</hi> and that their offspring ſhall not remain in it, 37 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.22.28. The which will be made good in the ever of the time to come.</p>
               <p>And whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.14. <hi>What ſhall we ſay then, is there <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs with God? God forbid.</hi> Whereas he ſaith then, thereby he ſheweth he hath his reference to the time to come. For as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaid according to this time, it ſhall be ſaid of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what hath God wrought, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.23. And ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth the deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the ſecond time, will be like that of the firſt. And whereas he ſaid in the 15. verſ. God ſaid to <hi>Moſes, I will have Mercy, on whom I will have Mercy: and I will have compaſſion on whom I will have compaſſion.</hi> Whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 16. <hi>So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth Mercy.</hi> By this then, the Apoſtle hath his reference to the then time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38506:23"/>And therefore he ſaith in the 17 verſ. <hi>The Scripture ſaith unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>even for this ſame purpoſe have I raiſed thee up, that I might ſhew my power in thee, and that my name might be declared through all the Earth.</hi> Now in the Hebrew it is no otherwiſe writ, then that God made him ſtand: For they being <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, God therefore then made him ſtand, till he came in the Clouds to drown them in the Sea. For tho' God did not harden him in Wickedneſs or Cruelty, yet he did in unbelief of his Power, that he and his Hoſt might follow after <hi>Iſrael</hi> and be drowned in the Sea. So again when the Lord comes in the Clouds, the wicked <hi>Edomites</hi> will then be deſtroyed, when their Children will be ſpared; for them that harden themſelves in Wickedneſs and Cruelty, God chuſes ſuch to harden in unbelief of his coming, that he may thereby overtake them at unawares. And when the Maſter of the Houſe riſeth up to Judgment, then he will have mercy on whom he will have mercy; and then his Mercy will be ſhewed according to his Promiſe, and his Puniſhments according to his Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. For therein they ſhall not reſiſt his will, for then it is not any ones willing and running, can bring them in Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Promiſes: For then God according to his Word will ſhew forth his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and make ſome Veſſels to Honour, and ſome to Diſhonour. At which time, verſ. 23.24. <hi>He will make known the Riches of his Glory on the Veſſels of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which he had before prepared unto Glory; even us whom he hath called, not of the Jews only, but alſo of the Gentiles.</hi> This the Apoſtle ſpeaks of them that were then in a peculiar manner called in, whom he had before well inſtructed in theſe matters about which he wrote unto them for he ſaith he had declared the whole counſel of God, by which he ſays he was <hi>clear from the Blood of all Men,</hi> Acts 20.26, 27. But theſe things were hard for us to underſtand: who ſince t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38506:23"/>of the Pope know nothing of this matter, he hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned it for a Hereſie.</p>
               <p>Now St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſeveral meanings, according to the ſeveral occaſions he had to expreſs himſelf. As when the firſt Gentile Churches were brought out of Idolatry, he ſaid unto them, it was not for any works of Righteouſneſs which they had done, but according to his Mercy he ſaved them, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. And to all that embraced the Faith, He ſaid, they muſt <hi>run for the Prize,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. And that ſuch ſhould <hi>reap if they faint not, Gal</hi> 6.9. And whereas he ſaith, ye are ſaved by Grace, and not by Works; Is thereby to ſhew, That none can be ſaved by Works ſtanding alone, without the Grace and Mercy of God through Chriſt; But the tender of God's Grace being on conditions, we muſt in this Life perform the conditions, if we will in time to come inherit the Promiſes. But when the Maſter of the Houſe is riſen up to Judgment, then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth Mercy: For then God will ſhew Mercy to <hi>Iſrael</hi> according to his promiſe, and puniſh the Diſobedient under the Goſpel according to his Threatnings. But we not knowing theſe diſtinctions, it hath occaſioned endleſs Controverſie among us: And had not St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words had their ſeveral ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies, he had writ a parcel of contradictions: and if ſo, he had thereby made all that he had ſaid as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Not all Sleep.</head>
               <p>AND whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52. <hi>We ſhall not all Sleep, but we ſhall all be changed in a moment, at the last Trumpet.</hi> Now the queſtion is, what <hi>We</hi> the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of? Whether it be both good and bad, or only the ſaved that will
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38506:24"/>be thus ſuddenly changed. To which I anſwer, it is not the bad that will be thus ſuddenly changed, neither the generality of them that are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that will be the <hi>We,</hi> the Apoſtle here mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. For <hi>Iſrael</hi> is to return into their own Land, when the great Trumpet is blown, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.13 And then it is the New everlaſting Covenant will be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht, and then it is God will reſt in his Love to his People. Therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 52. As it is written, Death is ſwallowed up in Victory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.8. <hi>For then it is the rebuke of his People</hi> Iſrael <hi>God will take away from off all the Earth.</hi> But this will not be done in the twinkling of an Eye, therefore can have no reference to the <hi>We,</hi> that are to be ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly changed. And ſo by this <hi>We,</hi> the Apoſtle appears only to have his reference to them in that time, rather than to the Elect remnant, which was to remain to the end of the World undeceived. For in that he ſaid we ſhall not all Sleep, as expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the returning of the Lord in their Day, as by his writing it does further appear in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> Chap. 4. verſ. 17. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <hi>Then we which are alive, and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air.</hi> For he knew that they were fore-choſen for the Glorious Tabernacle, as well as thoſe that Sleep, when raiſed. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12. <hi>That we ſhould be to the Praiſe of his Glory, who firſt truſted in Chriſt.</hi> Whereby it is evident to all by his ſaying <hi>We,</hi> he had but herein his reference to them in that time that did firſt truſt in Chriſt, and were fore-choſen, <hi>that God in them might ſhew forth the exceeding Riches of his Grace in the Ages to come,</hi> Epheſ. 2.7. For they being fore-choſen for the Glorious Tabernacle, he knew there was no get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up there, but by being taken up in the Clouds to meet the Lord in the Air, where this Glorious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38506:24"/>Manſion is to be placed <hi>over all</hi> Iſrael's <hi>aſſemblies, and for their Covert,</hi> Iſa. 4.5, 6. And that he did expect the coming of the Lord in their Day is farther evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, till ſuch time he wrote the Second Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> wherein he then wrote to them not to think that the Day of the Lord was at Hand, Chap. 2.2. The which had he not before thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he would not have had occaſion to have wrote to have brought them out of that miſtake.</p>
               <p>Now ſome Men had rather continue in their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, and let God's Glory and Man's Salvation lye at ſtake: And ſo the People daſh themſelves in pieces, about their ſeveral Opinions like ſo many Potſherds, rather than themſelves be found in a miſtake, or ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to encounter with a difficulty: The which they know they muſt do, without they have orders from Authority, and an agreement among themſelves. For altho' moſt of all the Teachers are in ſome one thing, more right than the other, yet the height of Man's mind is ſo great, that they will not in the leaſt yield one to the other. For tho' the greateſt part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are righter than the Diſſenting party in ſome things, yet in ſome other things the Diſſenting party is righter than they. In that they ingage none in Oaths at Baptiſm: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that they do not now allow any Lord-like digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Church. And as for either Pope or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as far as they own the Truth; all that have the true fear of God before their Eyes, are bound to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. But the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> are not willing to own there is a Redemption in the World to come, becauſe the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> own there is a return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſome from the place of Puniſhment, but the place of Separation, will not be found the Popes Purgatory, for the Prieſts to pray them out for a piece of Money. For as the Tree falls there it lies, till the Judge's time is to remove it. And to prove
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38506:25"/>that there is a Redemption for ſome in the Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to come, I ſhall only here cite two or three Quotations of Scripture out of many, for brevity ſake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, that <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom God hath concluded in unbelief when the Lord again comes will be deliver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed <hi>out of the Pit wherein there is no Water,</hi> Zech. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. The which are now <hi>Priſoners of hope, verſ.</hi> 12. Rom. 11.26, 32. And the Children that were Slain by <hi>Herod,</hi> will then return <hi>from the Land of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to their own Border,</hi> Jer. 31.15, 16, 17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. Chap. 2.5, 6. Chap. 4.9, 10. The word <hi>All</hi> in Scripture doth not include the whole, but it doth the major part. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Teachers of all parties not to be offended, for I am to ſpeak the Truth of all ſides.</p>
               <p>Some ſay that I do not write in a Scholaſtick method, and that I heap Scriptures one upon the Back of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As for writing in a Scholaſtick method, I never deſire to do it, for by that method any one may turn the Scriptures as a Noſe of Wax which way they pleaſe, and as for my heaping Scriptures together, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the only way to make the true meaning of the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appear what it is, when I have a Cloud of Witneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to prove what I affirm, and likewiſe mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plain to the underſtanding what did firſt ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by ſlight examination to appear to be anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing than what it really is; for the Bible hang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one upon another from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Revelations,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by making plainly appear that all the Propheſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Chriſt, and the Apſtoles do agree in one and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame thing it is the moſt Convincing way to confir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Truth of the Scriptures, and to bring the Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple into a right underſtanding of the ſame, the whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by the Scholaſtick way the Learned Scholars take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with, it is impoſſible for them to do, ſhould th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> live to the Age of <hi>Methuſalem.</hi> I hope the wiſe Heart will conſider theſe things.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
